I was 23 years old when I first heard about Reproductive Justice. I was working at Women with a Vision, where I learned that Reproductive Justice was defined by Sister Song as: One: A woman's right to decide if and when she will have a baby and the conditions under which she will give birth. Two: A woman's right to decide if she will not have a baby and her options for preventing or ending a pregnancy. And three: A woman's right to parent the children she already has in safe and healthy environments without fear of violence from individuals or the government. I've always wanted to be a mother. Growing up, I heard all about the joys of motherhood. I used to dream of watching my womb weave wonder into this world. See, I knew I was young. But I figured, it couldn't hurt to start planning for something so big, so early. But now, I'm 26 years old. And I don't know if I have what it takes to stomach motherhood in this country. See, over the years, America has taught me more about parenting than any book on the subject. It has taught me how some women give birth to babies and others to suspects. It has taught me that this body will birth kin who are more likely to be held in prison cells than to hold college degrees. There is something about being Black in America that has made motherhood seem complicated. Seem like, I don't know what to do to raise my kids right and keep them alive. Do I tell my son not to steal because it is wrong, or because they will use it to justify his death? Do I tell him that even if he pays for his Skittles and sweet tea there will still be those who will watch him and see a criminal before child; who will call the police and not wait for them to come. Do I even want the police to come? Too many Sean Bells go off in my head when I consider calling 911. I will not take it for Oscar Grant-ed that they will not come and kill my son. So, we may have gotten rid of the nooses, but I still consider it lynching when they murder Black boys
Tenía 23 años cuando por primera vez escuché sobre la justicia reproductiva. Trabajaba en "Woman With A Vision", donde aprendí que Sister Song definió la justicia reproductiva como: Uno, el derecho de la mujer de decidir si quiere tener un bebé y cuándo tenerlo y las condiciones en las que dará a luz. Dos: el derecho de la mujer a decidir no tener un bebé y elegir opciones para prevenir o interrumpir un embarazo. Y tres: el derecho de la mujer a criar los hijos que ya tiene en ambientes seguros y sanos sin miedo a la violencia por parte de individuos o el gobierno. Siempre he querido ser madre. En mi infancia, escuché todo sobre la dicha de ser madre. Solía soñar con ver mi vientre gestar un milagro y traerlo a este mundo. Bueno, yo sabía que era joven. Pero supuse que no sería malo comenzar a planificar algo tan grande, tan anticipadamente. Pero ahora tengo 26 años. Y no sé si tengo lo que se necesita para ser madre en este país. Bueno, durante años, Estados Unidos me ha enseñado más sobre crianza que cualquier libro sobre la materia. Me ha enseñado cómo algunas mujeres dan a luz a bebés y otras dan a luz a sospechosos. Me ha ensañado que este cuerpo dará a luz a familiares que serán más propensos a ser encarcelados en prisión que obtener un título de licenciado. Existe algo acerca de ser negro en Estados Unidos que ha hecho que el ser madre parezca complicado. Que parezca, no sé qué hacer para criar a mis hijos correctamente y mantenerlos con vida. ¿Le digo a mi hijo que no robe porque eso es malo, o porque ellos lo usarán para justificar su muerte? ¿Le digo que incluso si paga por sus Skittles y su té dulce aun así existirán quienes lo mirarán y verán como criminal antes que como niño y llamarán a la policía y no esperarán que llegue? ¿Quiero realmente que llegue la policía? Demasiados casos Sean Bell pasan por mi mente cuando considero llamar al 911. No daré por sentado que no llegarán a matar a mi hijo. Así, puede que nos hayamos deshecho de los ahorcamientos, pero aún lo considero linchamiento cuando asesinan niños negros
and leave their bodies for four hours in the sun. As a historical reminder that there is something about being Black in America that has made motherhood sound like mourning. Sound like one morning I could wake up and see my son as a repeat of last week's story. Sound like I could wake up and realize the death of my daughter wouldn't even be newsworthy. So you can't tell me that Sandra Bland is the only Black woman whose violence deserves more than our silence. What about our other dark-skinned daughters in distress whose deaths we have yet to remember? What about our children whose lives don't fit neatly between the lives of your genders? See, apparently, nothing is a great protector if you come out of a body that looks like this. See, there is something about being Black in America that has made motherhood sound like something I'm not sure I look forward to. I've written too many poems about dead Black children to be naïve about the fact that there could one day be a poem written about my kids. But I do not want to be a mother who gave birth to poems. I do not want a stanza for a son nor a line for a little girl nor a footnote for a child who doesn't fit into this world. No. I do not want children who will live forever in the pages of poetry, yet can't seem to outlive me. (Applause) I was invited to the TEDWomen conference
y dejan sus cuerpos durante cuatro horas al sol. Como un recordatorio histórico de que existe algo acerca de ser negro en Estados Unidos que hace que la maternidad se parezca a estar de luto. Que parezca que despertaré una mañana y veré a mi hijo como la repetición de la noticia de la semana pasada. Que parezca que despertaré y entenderé que la muerte de mi hija ni siquiera será de interés periodístico. No pueden decirme que Sandra Bland es la única mujer negra cuya violencia merece más que nuestro silencio. ¿Qué hay de nuestras hijas de piel oscura en peligro cuyas muertes aún nos quedan por recordar? ¿Qué hay de nuestros hijos cuyas vidas no encajan bien en las vidas de los géneros determinados? Al parecer, nada te protege realmente si vienes desde un cuerpo que luce así. Verán, existe algo acerca de ser negro en Estados Unidos que hace que ser madre suene como algo que no sé si aún anhelo. He escrito muchos poemas sobre la muerte de niños negros para parecer ingenua acerca del hecho de que un día podría haber un poema acerca de mis hijos. Pero no quiero ser un monstruo que da a luz poemas. No quiero una estrofa en lugar de un hijo ni un verso en lugar de una niña pequeña ni una nota en vez de un niño que no encaja en este mundo. No. No quiero hijos que vivan para siempre en las páginas de poesía, y que aun así parezcan no vivir más que yo. (Aplausos) Me invitaron a la conferencia TEDWomen
to perform a poem. But for me, poetry is not about art and performance. It is a form of protest. Yesterday, during rehearsal, I was told that there had been two to three recent TED Talks about Black Lives Matter. That maybe I should cut down my TED Talk so it could "just" be about Reproductive Justice. But that poem and this talk is fundamentally about my inability to separate the two. I was 21 years old -- (Applause) I was 21 years old when Trayvon Martin was murdered. Trayvon Martin, a 17-year-old Black boy, a Black child, reminded me reminded us how little this nation actually values Black life. The hashtag #BlackLivesMatter
para representar un poema. Pero para mí, la poesía no se trata de arte y representación. Es una forma de protesta. Ayer, durante el ensayo, me dijeron que había habido dos o tres charlas TED sobre Black Lives Matter. Y que tal vez debería acortar mi charla TED para que fuera solo sobre "justicia reproductiva". Pero ese poema y esta charla son fundamentalmente sobre mi incapacidad para separarlas. Tenía 21 años... (Aplausos) Tenía 21 años cuando Trayvon Martin fue asesinado. Trayvon Martin, un niño negro de 17 años, un niño negro, me recordó, nos recordó lo poco que esta nación valora las vidas de la gente negra. El hashtag #BlackLivesMatter
became the most recognized call for Black people and our children
se convirtió en la demanda más reconocida para que la gente negra y nuestros hijos
to live in safe environments and healthy communities without fear from violence from individuals or the state or government. Months later, when George Zimmerman was not held responsible for murdering Trayvon Martin, I heard Sybrina Fulton, Trayvon Martin's mother, speak. Her testimony so deeply impacted me that I found myself constantly asking, what would it mean to mother in the United Stated of America in this skin? What does motherhood really mean, when for so many who look like me it is synonymous with mourning? Without realizing it, I had begun to link the Reproductive Justice framework and the Movement for Black Lives. As I learned more about Reproductive Justice at Women With A Vision, and as I continued to be active in the Movement for Black Lives, I found myself wanting others to see and feel these similarities. I found myself asking: Whose job is it in times like this to connect ideas realities and people? I want to dedicate this talk and that poem to Constance Malcolm. She is the mother of Ramarley Graham who was another Black child who was murdered before their time. She reminded me once over dinner, as I was struggling to write that poem, that it is the artist's job to unearth stories that people try to bury with shovels of complacency and time. Recently, Toni Morrison wrote, "In times of dread, artists must never choose to remain silent. There is no time for self-pity, no room for fear." Yesterday, during rehearsal, when I was told that I should "maybe cut the Black Lives Matter portion from my talk,"
vivan en ambientes seguros y comunidades saludables sin miedo a la violencia de individuos o del Estado o el gobierno. Meses más tarde, cuando George Zimmerman no se consideró responsable de asesinar a Trayvon Martin, escuché a Sybrina Fulton, la madre de Trayvon Martin, hablar. Su testimonio me impactó tan profundamente que me encontré cuestionando constantemente qué significaría ser madre en los Estados Unidos de América con esta piel. ¿Qué significa realmente ser madre, cuando para tantos que lucen como yo es sinónimo de estar de luto? Sin darme cuenta, he empezado a conectar el contexto de la justicia reproductiva y el movimiento por la gente negra. Mientras aprendía sobre justicia reproductiva en Women With A Vision, y mientras seguía activa en el movimiento por la gente negra, me encontré queriendo que otros vieran y sintieran estas similitudes. Me encontré preguntándome: ¿En momentos como estos, quién se encarga de conectar ideas, realidades y personas? Quiero dedicar esta charla y este poema a Constance Malcolm. Ella es la madre de Ramarley Graham que fue otro niño negro que murió prematuramente. Ella me recordó una vez en una cena, mientras yo me esforzaba por escribir ese poema, que ese es el trabajo del artista el desenterrar historias que algunos intentan enterrar con palas de complacencia y tiempo. Recientemente, Toni Morrison escribió que en tiempos de temor, los artistas nunca deben elegir guardar silencio. No hay lugar para la autocompasión, no hay lugar para el miedo. Ayer, durante el ensayo, cuando me dijeron que debería "tal vez cortar la parte sobre Black Lives Matter de mi charla",
I found myself fearful for a moment. Fearful that again our stories were being denied the very stages they deserve to be told on. And then I remembered the words I had just spoken. "In times of dread, artists must never choose to remain silent. There is no time for self-pity. (Applause) And no room for fear." And I have made my choice. And I am always choosing. Thank you. (Applause)
sentí temor. Temía que otra vez se les negara a nuestras historias los propios lugares donde merecen ser contadas. Y luego recordé las palabras que acababa de decir. En tiempos de temor, los artistas nunca deben elegir guardar silencio. No hay lugar para la autocompasión. (Aplausos) Y no hay lugar para el miedo. Y tomé mi decisión. Y siempre estoy decidiendo. Gracias. (Aplausos)